# Germán Idoate Gil - Senior Engineer in Control Systems





g.idoate92@gmail.com (+41) 0767757052



german-idoate-gil



Rothenburgstrasse 28, Emmenbrücke, Luzern, Switzerland, 6020

## **Profile**

I am a Senior Control Systems Engineer with over 10 years of experience in product development within diverse industries.

Throughout the past decade, I have built my career on technical excellence in mechanical and control systems,

advancing to leadership roles where I guide and develop engineering teams to deliver across the entire product lifecycle. My strong communication skills empower my teams to achieve exceptional results and drive business success for every company I join.

# **Professional experience**

**Company**: Trane Technologies (Spain)

Jan 2024 - Today

Role: Engineering Project leader

#### **Responsibilities and achievements**

Technical leader of the next generation of refrigeration control systems:

- Key contributor on the implementation of global control dev. processes (MBSE, CI/CD)
- Influence the project direction and outcomes to align with corporate strategic goals
- Single point of contact for the engineering team
- Engineering leader for hardware and software design in a >€1m development project
- Tech leadership of 10x engineers' (mechanical, controls, electrical, thermodynamics...)

**Company**: McLaren Automotive Ltd. (Spain and UK)

Aug 2018 – Dec 2023

Role: Senior Powertrain Controls engineer

#### Responsibilities and achievements

Powertrain systems SW and Calibration project leadership (up to 4x programs in parallel)

- Manage the technology roadmap for Control SW design (Engine and Gearbox control)
- Product attribute targets and features definition
- Technical management of the SW supplier in >€5m budget projects
- Manage stakeholder relationships and influence senior management decisions through regular reporting of project KPIs, timing and quality, ensuring alignment with strategic goals

Technical reference for powertrain system control

- Powertrain controls leader for 5x programs McLaren GT, Speedtail, 765LT, Elva and 750S
- Motion Control expertise: Torque Structure, Torque model, Clutch model, Engine cooling, Derating and protection, Launch Control, Gearshifts
- Engine and Gearbox control integration with other of the vehicle systems (electric drive, ESP...)
- Data analysis and RCA in vehicle systems: hybrid powertrains, transmission, traction control
- In-vehicle testing conducting tests in proving ground and race track environment

**Company**: Nissan Motor Corporation (UK) Sept 2015 – Aug 2018

**Role**: Base engine calibration engineer – engine dyno engineer

### **Education**

2014-2015 - Motorsport engineering MSc. (90 ECTS)

Institution: Oxford Brookes University (UK)

2010-2014 - Mechanical Engineering University Degree (240 ECTS)

Institution: Public University of Navarre (Spain)

#### Personal skills

Team leading, Strategic thinking, Communication, Project planning, Decision making, Teamworking, Problem solving, Negotiation, Fast learner

#### **Technical skills**

### **Product development**

Product benchmarking, market requirements, system requirements and modelling (MBSE, ISO15288), functional safety (ISO-26262), controls model architecture, CAN Networks, mechanical integration, engine and gearbox calibration

#### Tools and programming languages

Microsoft Office, DevOps infrastructure, Requirements management (DOORS), Version control (GitHub, SVN), Calibration and test (ETAS INCA & MDA, CANape, CANDB++), Agile methodology (JIRA, Mantis), Coding (VSCode, Matlab, Simulink), C and Python

#### **Computing Science**

As part of my personal and professional development, I am actively self-studying computer science using online resources, including courses, books, and technical materials. My learning journey and progress are documented in this GitHub repository - <a href="https://github.com/gidoate/cs learning">https://github.com/gidoate/cs learning</a>

# Languages

Spanish (native)	Full proficiency (speaking, reading and writing)
English (proficient – C1)	Full proficiency (speaking, reading and writing)
Italian (professional – B2)	Able to follow a meeting and to read/write emails
French (intermediate – B1)	Able to read/write emails limited spoken communication